Joe: The ‘Autism act’ was the first
legislation to specifically focus on
Autism, even though the other acts do
support individuals in different ways.
Because of the Act, most councils now
have a diagnosis pathway for adults,
a specific ‘Autism Lead’ and make sure
that every autistic person has the
right to a social care assessment,
something which was difficult for
many autistic people in the past.
Beth: The ‘Fulfilling and Rewarding Lives’
strategy aimed to improve physical and
mental health, reduce crime and substance
misuse, reduce dependency on benefits and
raise awareness amongst professionals,
also to make sure diagnostic services are
available and ensure that transitions into
adult services are managed successfully.
Joe: ‘Think autism’ further built
on this by improving all aspects and
helping those with autism get into work,
developing skills and independence.
These strategies outline some of the
areas that needed to be improved,
such as autism awareness training,
access to a diagnosis and assessment
and local service and support.
Beth: Importantly, the strategies and
guidance state that a diagnosis of any
autistic spectrum condition, including
Asperger syndrome or high-functioning
autism, is a reason to assess somebody for
support and though it does not guarantee
services will be provided, assessment
should be carried out and look at the
person rather than their diagnosis.
Joe: There is emphasis on aiming to
improve public services for people with
autism, such as transport, leisure,
employment and the police, to get
better at adjusting to, and meeting
the needs of, people with autism.
Local authorities need to keep and
provide data about autism in their area,
such as the numbers of autistic people
known about, the range of need for the
support for them to live independently
and the age profile of people with autism.
Beth: While progress has been made
since the Autism Act, there is still
much to be done in society to show that
autistic people have the same rights to
life and independence as other people.
If these strategies are successful
and can change how society views
autism, this can lead to real
improvements in the day-to-day lives
of autistic people, as well as carers
and professionals that support them.